Finding Aid for College of Engineering (University of Michigan) publications, 1873-2015
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
College of Engineering (University of Michigan) publications 1873-2015
University of Michigan. College of Engineering.
Publications produced by the College of Engineering and some of its academic departments and administrative units as student organizations. Includes annual reports, briefing papers, brochures and pamphlets, bulletins and college catalogs, calendars of college events, histories, manuals, newsletters such as the Michigan Engineer, programs, proposals, reports, songbooks, and statistics.
977 Bimu C141 2
21.3 linear feet
771.7 MB
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The Publications were transferred from the College of Engineering (Donor no. 1884 ) in several accessions beginning in 1937. Printed material is received on a regular basis.
The records are open for research.
The Department of Engineering was established at the University of Michigan in 1858, four years after engineering courses were first offered. In 1871 Professor DeVolson Wood suggested that the Department of Engineering be separated from the Department of Literature, Science, and the Arts, but it was not until 1895 that such a separation occurred. In that year, the departments of civil, mechanical, and electrical engineering were organized into a distinct Department of Engineering and Professor Charles Ezra Greene was appointed dean. The department was to be governed by the faculty, with the dean handling admission of students. Mortimer Elwyn Cooley, a professor of mechanical engineering at the University since 1881, was appointed dean upon Greene's death in 1903 and took office in 1904. He served as dean until 1928 and was succeeded by Herbert Charles Sadler, a professor of naval architecture and marine engineering who had been on the University of Michigan faculty for thirty-nine years. Sadler resigned the deanship in 1937 and was followed by Henry Clay Anderson, a professor in the Mechanical Engineering Department. Anderson died in 1939 and was replaced by Ivan Charles Crawford, a civil engineer who had served as dean of the colleges of engineering at the University of Idaho and the University of Kansas. He was dean of the College of Engineering at Michigan from 1940 to 1951. The sixth dean of the college, George Granger Brown, held the post from 1951 to 1957. He was followed by Stephen S. Attwood, 1957-1965, Gordon Van Wylen, 1965-1972, and David V. Ragone, 1972-1980. Hansford W. Farris served as acting dean from 1980 until the 1981 appointment of James J. Duderstadt. Duderstadt resigned in 1986 to become provost and vice president for academic affairs for the university. He was succeeded as dean by Charles M. Vest, 1986-1989. Daniel E. Atkins, III, was interim dean from 1989 to 1990, Peter M. Banks served as dean from 1990 to 1996, and Stephen W. Director assumed the deanship in 1996.
In 1905 the Regents of the University approved the establishment of a chair of architecture in the Department of Engineering. With this decision, courses in architecture were once again made available. (In 1876-1877 William Le Baron Jenney had lectured as Professor of Architecture and Design in the new Department of Architecture and Design, which had been established in 1873 within the School of Mines. Due to a lack of funds, these courses were suspended in 1877. Jenney left the university in 1880, having fulfilled his obligations as architect for the university's new museum).
By 1913 the Department of Engineering had become the Departments of Engineering and Architecture. The title was changed in 1915 to the Colleges of Engineering and Architecture. In 1931 the College of Architecture became an independent unit.
In 1920, under the leadership of Dean Cooley, the Department of Engineering Research was formed as a means of promoting cooperation between the university, the state, and private industry. Through this department private industries sponsored research projects that would be conducted by College of Engineering faculty members. In addition to providing financial assistance, such projects enabled students and faculty members to engage in research of current interest in a wide variety of areas. Beginning in 1940, projects sponsored by the federal government were undertaken by the department and in 1948 the department was reorganized as the Engineering Research Institute. In 1957-1958 the Research Institute became an administrative unit of the university.
Before World War II the College of Engineering focused primarily on undergraduate education and on providing students with practical experience and skill. The many technological advances that occurred during and after the war prompted an increased emphasis on research and theory and a corresponding emphasis on graduate education. This shift was reflected in the development of research facilities on the North Campus beginning in the 1950s with the Cooley Laboratory. Technological advances also prompted changes in the curriculum and structure of the college. Some new departments were created, such as Nuclear Engineering. Other departments shifted their emphases; Aeronautical Engineering, for example, became Aerospace Engineering. The records reflect these developments as well as the broad changes which took place in the College of Engineering from its inception in the late nineteenth century up to the 1970s.
In the 1980s the College of Engineering continued to meet the technological challenges of the future through instruction, research, and development. Most of the college was relocated to North Campus in the early 1980s. This was followed by additional construction and renovation to house the college's major research initiatives, including the Center for Advanced Scientific Computation, created to study the applications of supercomputing, and the Center for Robotics and Integrated Manufacturing (CRIM), established in 1981 to examine the future needs of the modern manufacturing industry.
Funding was a major concern of the college in the 1980s. The tightened budgets of the previous decade resulted in increased faculty teaching loads and decreased research resources. The college sought to rectify this situation by appealing to the state for increased funding, attempting to keep the University of Michigan's College of Engineering on par with its peer institutions. As it looked toward the 1990s, the goals of the college, as stated in College of Engineering Briefing Material 1988-89 (Box 52, Folder: Briefing Materials), were twofold: first, "to establish preeminence in certain areas of special relevance to the state and region," such as manufacturing science and technology, machine intelligence, systems integration, and engineering design; and second, "to establish preeminence in certain areas of research and education of anticipated importance to the future of technology," including advanced optics and electronics, materials science and technology, information technology, and biotechnology.
By 1996, new programs had been added, most notably a Department of Biomedical Engineering and an Engineering Research Center for Reconfigurable Machining; the latter was chosen by the National Science Foundation to be the largest center in the country for basic research in manufacturing. The college also continued to increase its presence on North Campus, adding a carillon tower, the Robert H. Lurie Engineering Center, and a new library called the Media Union. The latter, shared with the schools of Architecture and Urban Planning, Music, and Art, was an ambitious project, described as a place where "new information technology will create a 'virtual' community of thinkers, allowing face-to-face dialogue and collaboration across thousands of miles".
Deans of the College of Engineering
1895-1903 Charles Ezra Greene
1903-1928 Mortimer E. Cooley
1927-1928 George W. Patterson, Acting Dean
1928-1937 Herbert Charles Sadler
1937-1939 Henry C. Anderson
1940-1951 Ivan C. Crawford
1951-1957 George Granger Brown
1957-1965 Stephen S. Attwood
1965-1972 Gordon Van Wylen
1972-1980 David V. Ragone
1980-1981 Hansford W. Farris, Acting Dean
1981-1986 James J. Duderstadt
1986-1989 Charles M. Vest
1989-1990 Daniel E. Atkins, III, Interim Dean
1990-1996 Peter M. Banks
1996- Stephen W. Director
The College of Engineering Publications consist of printed material produced by the College of Engineering and some of its academic departments and administrative units as student organizations. It includes annual reports, briefing papers, brochures and pamphlets, bulletins and college catalogs, calendars of college events, histories, manuals, newsletters such as the Michigan Engineer, programs, proposals, reports, songbooks, and statistics. Publications of some academic departments are cataloged separately. The College of Engineering Publications (13 linear feet) are divided into four series; Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, Topical Publications, and Student Publications.
The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the College of Engineering. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication.
The Sub-Unit Publications series contains publications from subordinate offices, departments, programs, laboratories and organizations within the College of Engineering. These publications are arranged alphabetically by the creating sub-unit.
The Topical Publications series includes publications which document specific events or activities such as anniversary celebrations, convocations, faculty awards or memorials, graduation exercises, or one-time conferences hosted by the College of Engineering.
The Student Publications series contains publications published by student groups within the College of Engineering. The specific student organizations are arranged alphabetically by name of the organization.
Some publications (or their successors) may no longer be available in print but are available on the school s website.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Bioengineering Program.; University of Michigan. Center for Research on Integrated Manufacturing.; University of Michigan. Computer-Aided Engineering Network.; University of Michigan. Industry Program.; University of Michigan. Michigan Engineering Television Network.; University of Michigan. Minority Engineering Program Office.; University of Michigan. North Campus Planning Committee.; Society of Women Engineers.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.
Contributors:
Tau Beta Pi. Gamma Chapter (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Bioengineering Program.; University of Michigan. Center for Research on Integrated Manufacturing.; University of Michigan. Michigan Engineering Television Network.; University of Michigan. Minority Engineering Program Office.; University of Michigan. North Campus Planning Committee.; Society of Women Engineers.; Tau Beta Pi. Gamma Chapter (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Industry Program.
Genre/Form:
Annual reports.; Pamphlets.; Catalogs, College.; Calendars.; Histories.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Programs.; Reports.; Student publications.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series (9.3 linear feet) includes brochures, bulletins, calendars of events, directories, histories, manuals, newsletters, planning documents, programs, proposals and reports. Bulletins or college catalogs, are arranged chronologically from 1881 to the present. There is a complete run of college bulletins (no bulletin was published in the 1997-1998 academic year). The print version of the bulletin is the authoritative source of admission information, course offerings and degree requirements. The college bulletins comprise almost three linear feet of the Unit Publications.
  This series also includes calendars titled The Week Ahead, The Two Weeks Ahead and This Month Ahead, which describe day-to-day activities of the college from 1967 to 1999. The College of Engineering published the directories Photographic Roster of the Engineering Faculty from 1969 to 1983 and the Faculty Directory from 1985 to 1998. Earlier faculty pictorial directories dating from 1960 to 1969 will be found under the "Industry Program" in the Sub-Unit Publications. There are several histories in the Unit Publications series, including the centennial history titled A Century of Engineering Education published in 1953, and an undated History--College of Engineering Buildings. There are several manuals which describe the community, university, and the College of Engineering in detail for incoming students. These include The Arch which was published in 1940 and What Every Engineer Should Know...Or...The Facts of Life (At Michigan), issued in 1949. To orientate its students the College of Engineering published The U-M Survival Guide to the Engineering Universe in 1991, and from 1995 to 1997, The First-Year Students' Handbook.
  There are several newsletters published by the college, including News, issued from 1981 to 1982, News from the College of Engineering published from 1982 to 1983, and The Michigan Engineer which was first released in 1984 and continues to the present. What's New in the College of Engineering was printed from 1992 to 1993. The Unit Publications series also includes planning documents describing the vision for the future of the college, programs for various events occurring at the college, proposals to various government agencies requesting support, and reports on improving engineering education and space utilization.
  - Annual Reports
    - 1970-1972 (Box 1)
    - College of Engineering, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Overview, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Briefing Papers
    - 1984-1988, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - 1950-2002 undated, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - College of Engineering, 1954-1995, undated (Box 1)
    - College of Engineering Descriptive Pamphlet, 1934 (Box 1)
    - Engineering Education at Michigan, undated (Box 1)
    - Engineering Education at Michigan, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
    - Engineering Education at Michigan: Crisis, Challenge, and Opportunity by James J. Duderstadt, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Engineering the Future, 1990-1993 (Box 1)
    - Inter-College Programs, undated (Box 1)
    - New Frontiers, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Budgets
    - Budget Planning 1982
      - Supporting Materials, 1982 (Box 1)
      - Status Report: Five Year Budget Plan, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Budget Planning Conference
      - Reports 1987-1988, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Bulletins (College Catalogs)
    - Department of Engineering Announcement, 1881-1900 (Box 1)
    - General Announcement, 1901-1905 (Box 1)
    - General Announcement, 1905-1913, 2 volumes bound volume (Box 1)
    - General Announcement, 1913-1917, 1 volumes bound volume (Box 2)
    - Courses in Study in the Department of Engineering, 1906-1915 (Box 2)
    - General Announcement, 1916-1928, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Announcement, 1929-2003
      - 1929-1963, 12 folders (Box 2)
      - 1964-1997, 17 folders (Box 3)
      - 1998-2006, 5 folders (Box 4)
      - 2003-2004, .PDF files
      - 2004-2005, .PDF files
      - 2005-2006, .PDF files
      - 2006-2007, .PDF and .ZIP files
      - 2007-2008, .PDF and .ZIP files
      - 2008-2009, .PDF and .ZIP files
      - 2009-2010, .PDF and .ZIP files
      - 2010-2011, .PDF and .ZIP files
      - 2011-2012, .PDF file
      - 2012-2013, .PDF files
      - 2015-2016 (Box 4)
    - Course Descriptions, 1998-1999 (Box 4)
    - Engineering Courses by Satellite, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Information for Graduate Students in Chemical Engineering, Materials Engineering, Metallurgical Engineering at the University of Michigan, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Program of Work, 1898-1902, 1903/04 (Box 4)
    - Six Year Course Special Announcement, 1908-1909 (Box 4)
    - Special Announcement: Directions for Registration and Classification, 1904-1927, 8 folders (Box 4)
    - Special Announcement, 1928-1946, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Calendars
    - Calendar of Events and Faculty News, 1967 (Box 4)
    - The Two Weeks Ahead, 1967-1978, 5 volumes (Box 5)
    - The Week Ahead, 1978-1981 (Box 5)
    - The Week Ahead, 1979-1981 (loose issues not bound with previous volume) (Box 5)
    - The Two Weeks Ahead, 1981-1989, 1 volumes (Box 5)
    - The Two Weeks Ahead, 1981-1989 (loose issues not bound with previous volume) (Box 5)
    - The Two Weeks Ahead, 1989-1998, 9 folders (Box 6)
    - This Month Ahead, 1998/99 (Box 6)
  - Christmas Cards
    - Cards undated (Box 6)
  - Directories
    - Assistant Professors (pictorial directory), [ca. 1980] (Box 6)
    - College of Engineering Administrative Offices, 1993 (Box 6)
    - Faculty Directory (pictorial directory) 1985-1998, 9 folders (Box 6)
    - Photographic Roster of the Engineering Faculty, 1969-1983, 7 folders (Box 6)
    - Research Laboratories and Centers, 1994 (Box 6)
  - Emblems
    - College Emblem undated (Box 6)
  - Exhibition Catalogs
    - Exhibits of the Departments, 1913-1916 (Box 6)
  - Fact Sheet
    - 1990 undated (Box 6)
  - Flyers
    - 1991 (Box 6)
  - Histories
    - A Century of Engineering Education, 1953 (Box 7)
    - The College of Engineering, 1944 (Box 7)
    - The College of Engineering and the Freshman Class of 1967, 1967 (Box 7)
    - College of Engineering Timeline, undated (Box 7)
    - History--College of Engineering Buildings, undated (Box 7)
    - A Short History and Some of the Graduates of the Department of Engineering of the University of Michigan, reprint 1908 (Box 7)
  - Invitations
    - 1989 (Box 7)
  - Manuals
    - The Arch, 1940 (Box 7)
    - The First-Year Students' Handbook, 1995-1997, 2007/08, 2008/09 (Box 7)
    - Getting Off to a Good Start, undated (Box 7)
    - Guidelines for Student Use of Facilities in the Robert H. Lurie Engineering Center (LEC), 1999 (Box 7)
    - The U-M Survival Guide to the Engineering Universe, 1991 (Box 7)
    - What Every Engineer Should Know...Or...The Facts of Life (At Michigan), 1949 (Box 7)
  - Maps
    - Map of GG Brown, undated (Box 7)
  - Newsletters
    - Michigan Engineer
      - 1984-1996 includes index, 13 folders (Box 7)
      - 1996-1999 (Box 22)
        (Outsized)
      - 2000-ongoing, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - News, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
    - News from the College of Engineering, 1982-1983 (Box 7)
    - What's New in the College of Engineering, 1992-1993, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - What's Up, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Planning Documents
    - Planning Document Update: The College of Engineering Status and Future, 1981 (Box 7)
    - A Unique Opportunity for Michigan's Future: An Investment in Engineering Excellence, Rationale and Plan, 1984, 2 volumes (Box 7)
    - A Unique Opportunity for Michigan's Future: An Investment in Engineering Excellence, Rationale and Plan, 1985 (Box 7)
  - Posters
    - 1993 (Box 7)
  - Press Releases
    - 1973-1984 (Box 7)
  - Proceedings
    - Proceedings of the Tenth Annual Conference on Highway Engineering Held at the University of Michigan, February 11 to 14, 1924, 1924 (Box 7)
  - Programs
    - An Account of the Presentation of an ASME Gold Emblem to Dean Mortimer E. Cooley, 1935 (Box 7)
    - Awards Dinner Dance, 1992-1994 (Box 7)
    - Endowed Scholarship and Fellowship Luncheon, 1997-2001 (Box 7)
    - Engineering Honors Luncheon or Supper, 1967-1989 (Box 7)
    - Excellence in Staff Service Awards, 1992, 2002 (Box 7)
    - Groundbreaking for the Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Laboratory, 1984 (Box 7)
    - International Symposium on Flow Visualization, 1983 (Box 7)
    - Natural Science Foundation Sponsored Forums and Workshops 1986, undated (Box 7)
    - Student Honors Brunch, 1992-1997, 2001 (Box 7)
    - Student Leadership Recognition Dinner, 1996-1998, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Proposals
    - An Application by the University of Michigan to the Research Excellence and Economic Development Fund, 1985 (Box 8)
    - Engineering Research Center for Next Generation Quality Control in Manufacturing--Real-Time Defect Prevention, 1989 (Box 8)
    - A Five Year Plan for Improving Instruction Primarily in computer Related Areas in the College of Engineering at the University of Michigan, Draft II, 1981 (Box 8)
    - Intense Energy Beam Interactions with Space Environments, 1985 (Box 8)
    - Proposed Engineering Research Center for Reconfigurable Machining Systems, 1996 (Box 8)
    - A Unique Opportunity for Michigan's Future: An Investment in Engineering Excellence: Rationale and Plan, 1985 (Box 8)
    - The University of Michigan--GM Advanced Engineering Staff Project Proposals for 1987-1988, 1987 (Box 8)
  - Regulations
    - Rules and Decisions of the Faculty, 1915-1934 (Box 8)
    - Rules of the Faculty of the College of Engineering, 1975-1981 (Box 8)
  - Reports
    - The College of Engineering: Status and Future
      - Decision Charts, 1981 (Box 8)
      - Planning Documents Update, 1981 (Box 8)
      - A Presentation for the Executive Officers, 1981 (Box 8)
    - Computer Graphics in the College of Engineering, 1974 (Box 8)
    - The Crisis Facing Engineering Education in Michigan: A Call for Action, 1985 (Box 8)
    - The Engineer of the Future: A Report on Engineering Education at the University of Michigan, undated (Box 8)
    - Making an Impact, 1997 (Box 8)
    - New Directions in System Science and Engineering, 1972 (Box 8)
    - The New Engineering Buildings, University of Michigan by Mortimer E. Cooley, 1902 (Box 8)
    - Report of the Space Study and Recommendations, 1959 (Box 8)
    - The University of Michigan--Aid Brazilian Program at the Instituto Tecnologico De Aeronautica: Final Report, 1967 (Box 8)
    - Utilization of Space, 1960 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1991-1995 (located in Box 13) (Box 8)
  - Song Books
    - Engineering Class 1916, undated (Box 8)
    - Engineering Society Song Book, 1921-1922, undated (Box 8)
  - Statistics
    - The Class of 1965 Five Years Later, 1970 (Box 8)
  - Surveys
    - Intellectual Inventory, 1984 (Box 8)
    - A Survey of Intellectual Activities, 1987 (Box 8)
  - Textbooks
    - Course 1: Problems, undated (Box 8)
    - Course 2: Supplementary Text and Problems, undated (Box 8)
    - Course 3: Supplementary Text and Problems, 1921 (Box 8)
    - Course 4: Problems, undated (Box 8)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications series (10 linear feet) includes material published by units within the college. Programs and centers represented within this series include the Accreditation Board of Engineering and Technology, Bioengineering Program, Center for Ergonomics, Center for Research on Integrated Manufacturing (CRIM), Center for Robotics and Integrated Manufacturing (CRIM), Computer Aided Engineering Network (CAEN), Electron Microbeam Analysis Laboratory, Continuing Engineering Education, and the Engineering Summer Conferences.
  Alumni Relations publications reflect involvement with specific engineering classes to help them organize reunions and keep in touch with other class members. There are directories and newsletters created for the various graduating classes from 1904 to 1993. There are also several regional directories of College of Engineering graduates. An all-college directory, published in 1991, is cataloged separately under the call number FImu C156 C697 1991.